Ever stumbled upon these three little dots in
Python and wondered what they are for?
Welcome to one minute Python, and today we'll be
talking about these three triple dots.
These dots are formally called ellipsis.
It's a unique built-in constant object.
Think of it like true, false or none. There is
only one instance of it.
You can compare triple dots with the ellipsis
object using its operator.
It evaluates to true.
And checking its type with type function reveals
it belongs to the ellipsis class.
Now, how do you actually use it?
One common place is as a placeholder in a function
or method definition.
It is used to create empty blocks,
similar to pass keyword.
Using ellipsis can sometimes serve as a more
explicit signal
that real code implementation is pending here.
It's especially useful in stubs or abstract
methods.
Ellipses are also used in type hinting.
In the first example, ellipsis acts as a wild card
for arguments.
It signifies a callable
that can accept any number or type of parameters.
Similarly, it's used with generic types like
tuples.
In the second example, it defines a tuple that
must start with an
integer, but can then be followed by any number of
additional integers.
It's a concise way to annotate variable length
sequences where you know the type of
the elements.
Finally, you will see this a lot when working with
Pydantic library.
When defining fields or parameters using ellipsis,
it tells the library that this field or parameter
is mandatory.
It must be provided when creating an object.
This is the same as assigning ellipsis to default
parameter.
Internally, Pydantic checks if default value is
the ellipsis
object, and if so, they mark the field as
required.
That's all for the ellipsis. Thanks for watching.